Finding Aid for Vice President for Student Affairs (University of Michigan) Records
Bentley Historical Library
Vice President for Student Affairs (University of Michigan) records
1908-2005
1941-1951
Bentley Historical Library
University of Michigan. Vice-President for Student Affairs.
87290 Bimu B7 2
41.5 linear feet (in 43 boxes)
University of Michigan administrative office, established as the Dean of Student Affairs in 1921, responsible for overseeing many aspects of non-academic student services and activities including at various times: counseling, financial aid, student housing, student activities and organizations, the health service, student discipline, and fraternities and sororities. Records provide extensive documentation of student life.
The record group (Donor 5013 ) was received beginning in 1967. Periodic accessions to continue.
Materials donated by Michigan Medicine (Donor no. 2289 ) were added to the collection in June 2019.
The record group is open to research, except for records in Box 36 which are restricted in accordance with university and applicable law. See Contents List for restrictions.
Access Restrictions for University of Michigan Records
University records are public records and once fully processed are generally open to research use. Records that contain personally identifiable information will be restricted in order to protect individual privacy. Certain administrative records are restricted in accordance with university policy as outlined below. The restriction of university records is subject to compliance with applicable laws, including the Michigan Freedom of Information Act.
Categories of Restricted Records
Student educational records: FERPA's protection of personally identifiable information in a student's education records ends at the time of a student's death and therefore is a matter of institutional policy. As a courtesy to the families of recently deceased students who were enrolled at the time of death, the University generally will not release information from their education records for five years without the consent of the deceased student's next of kin. Eighty-five (85) years after the date the records were first created, the University will presume that the student is deceased. Thereafter the student's education records will be open. Student records at the Bentley Historical Library are restricted for eighty-five (85) years, but may also be made available upon proof of the death of the student.
Restricted files are indicated in the contents list of the collection’s finding aid with a restriction note indicating the restriction type and the date of expiration.
For further information on the restriction policy and placing Freedom of Information Act requests for restricted material, consult the reference archivist at the Bentley Historical Library (bentley.ref@umich.edu) or the University of Michigan Freedom of Information Office website (https://foia.vpcomm.umich.edu/).
The position of vice-president for student services traces its institutional ancestry back through the vice-president for student affairs, to the director of the Office of Student Affairs, finally to the Office of the Dean of Students. Through all of these metamorphoses the office's primary responsibility was the administration of programs related to the life of the student outside of the classroom. This encompasses a broad spectrum of programs dealing with counseling, financial aid, student housing, student activities and organizations, the health service, student discipline, and fraternities. The office reflects the changing interests and composition of the student body and the increasing complexity of the University's administrative bureaucracy.
Joseph A. Bursley, the first dean of students, took office February 1, 1921, to fulfill the Regents' dictate to act "as friend, counselor and guide to the student body and to have the general oversight of its welfare and of its general activities." Given this open-ended directive, Bursley soon found need to add an assistant dean and support staff to meet his mission tending to the housing, financial, social, and moral needs of students. By the time Bursley retired in 1945, the pattern of assuming increasing responsibilities with a larger staff and more complex bureaucracy was well established.
The burgeoning bureaucracy, retirement of Bursley, and the University's growing enrollment combined to facilitate the creation of the Office of Student Affairs in September 1945. This was the first of a series of periodic efforts to define more clearly the duties of the various offices concerned with different aspects of students' lives outside the classroom. Erich A. Walter served as director of the Office of Student Affairs from 1945 until June 1954. Upon Walter's retirement, James A. Lewis was appointed vice-president for student affairs. This new title reflected the hierarchical nature of both the office and the university as a whole. Lewis stepped down in December 1964, after another reorganization of the office.
During the latter half of the 1960s and early 1970s the University of Michigan campus was affected by student unrest, focused on the war in Vietnam as well as campus and national issues. Sit-ins, teach-ins, and more violent forms of student protest demanded the attention of the vice-presidents of student affairs and the University administration in general. Campus unrest had an impact on the Office of the Vice-President of Student Affairs and precipitated yet another reorganization of the office, this time to make it more responsive to student input. Richard L. Cutler served from December 1964 until the completion of the office reorganization in July 1968. Barbara W. Newell became acting vice-president on August 1, 1968 and served until September 1970. Robert Knauss succeeded her as the vice-president of the renamed Office for Student Services and held the post until February 1972. The changing of the guard, ongoing reorganization efforts, and the shift in focus to service stand as institutional testimony of the University's response to the chaotic times.
The appointment of Henry Johnson as vice-president for student services in April 1972 brought a needed stability to the post and a measure of order to the situation. Under Johnson, structural changes were introduced to address the needs of some disaffected groups, who thought the University unresponsive to their needs. The offices of Minority Student Services and Disabled Student Services provided an official framework within which to advance interests. As time passed, the student body became less restive, and the vice-president turned his attention to more traditional aspects of non-academic student affairs. In January 1990 Henry Johnson was reassigned to the position of Vice President for Community Affair. Mary Ann Swain acted as interim vice president for student services from 1990 to 1992.
In 1992, Maureen Hartford began her tenure as the vice president for student affairs. Hartford was previously the vice provost for student affairs at Washington State University and quickly rose to the task by focusing on issues such as the Student Code of Conduct, alcohol abuse, living/learning programs and students rights and responsibilities. In April 1999, Hartford left her position to assume the presidency of Meredith College in North Carolina. E. Royster Harper, who had served as the senior associate vice president for student affairs and dean of students then assumed the role of the interim vice president for student affairs. In November 2000, Harper was appointed vice president of student affairs.
The records of the Vice President for Student Affairs are arranged by the major accessions which came to the library and thereunder by series, generally reflecting the tenure of particular deans or vice presidents. While the series for each dean/vice president is primarily material created during their tenure, there are frequently some files created by their predecessors.
Summary Contents List
(Pre 1989 Accession)
Joseph A. Bursley, 1913-1950 (primarily 1925-1946) (Boxes 1-2)
Erich A. Walter, 1925-1959 (primarily 1946-1954) (Box 2)
James A. Lewis, 1908-1964 (primarily 1954-1964) (Boxes 2-6)
Richard L. Cutler, 1950-1969 (primarily 1964-1968) (Boxes 7-8)
Barbara W. Newell, 1965-1970 (primarily 1968-1970) (Boxes 8-9)
Robert L. Knauss,1962-1973 (primarily 1970-1972) (Boxes 10-11)
Henry Johnson, 1950-1985 (primarily 1972-1985) (Boxes 11-18)
(1989-1991 Accessions)
Henry Johnson, 1950-1985 (primarily 1972-1985) (Boxes 19-37)
(1993 Accession)
Vice-Presidents Topical Files, ca. 1960- ca 1973 (Box 38)
(1994-1998 Accessions)
Vice Presidents Topical Files, ca. 1971-1992 (Box 39-40)
The records of the Vice-President for Student Services provide a unique perspective to the extracurricular life and customs of students at the University of Michigan and an insight to the development of the office of the vice-president. The records span the years 1908-1985 with the bulk of the material covering 1965-1985. The material from the early years is especially rich in documenting student life from the 1920s to the 1950s. The strongest feature of this collection is in documenting the administration's response to the changing needs of students, ranging from disciplining drinkers during Prohibition, dealings with fraternities up to 1960, reacting to student protests in the 1960s to the 1988 debate over the Student Code for Non-Academic Conduct. The papers also contain materials related to students' health, housing, organizations, and activism. The coverage of these areas varies across administrations as office reorganizations altered the focus and functions of Student Services.
This uneven documentation reflects the fact that, over time, different offices were created to handle more narrowly-defined areas of responsibility. Areas which had originally been handled by Dean Bursley under his broad conception of control over non-academic student life came to be administered by separate offices. Frequently the records of these administrative units were not included with the vice-president for student services records. To gain a more comprehensive understanding of student life, as refracted through the lens of University Administration, one should also refer to the records of the Housing Office and Student-Community Relations Office, and the papers of Peter Ostafin, director of housing.
The Vice-President for Student Services collection consists of correspondence, reports, memos, minutes, and financial reports generated by both the University Administration and students. These materials are arranged in chronological series by the administrative head in charge of students' extracurricular affairs. The seven series are: Joseph A. Bursley, 1913-1950; Erich A. Walter, 1925-1959; James A. Lewis, 1908-1964; Richard L. Cutler, 1950-1969; Barbara W. Newell, 1965-1970; Robert L. Knauss, 1962-1973; Henry Johnson, 1950-1985. This organizing scheme required some manipulation of the files, but it best enables the researcher to trace the changing nature of the student body concerns and the development of the office itself.
The researcher should note that the strict chronological sequencing of the series was not possible. This was due in large part to a series of office reorganizations which resulted in some files created during Bursley or Walter's tenure ending up in later series. The most significant move here resulted in Lewis' series containing a good deal of Bursley and Walter materials on fraternities and student organizations. Lewis created the fraternities subseries in 1959 and compiled the student organization subseries during a May 1963, office reorganization. The researcher should also be conscious that early series contain a variety of materials which may not reflect the full scope of Bursley, Walter, or Lewis' responsibilities. Gaps are also discernible in the later series, but these are more readily fleshed out by referring to other University collections.
Greek letter societies -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Minority college students.; Tutors and tutoring.; Veterans -- Education -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Greek letter societies -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Handicapped college students -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Minority college students -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Campus Broadcasting Network.; Madelon Pound House (University of Michigan); Michigan Student Assembly.; Michigan Union.; Project Community.; University of Michigan. Drug Education Project.; University of Michigan. Office of Student Services.; University of Michigan -- Students -- Societies, etc.; University of Michigan. University Health Service.; University of Michigan -- Student housing.; Black Action Movement (University of Michigan); University of Michigan. Dean of Students.; University of Michigan -- Students.; University of Michigan -- Students -- Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; University of Michigan -- Students -- Discipline.; University of Michigan. Student Legal Services.; University of Michigan -- Students -- Social life and customs -- 1931-1940.; University of Michigan -- Students -- Social life and customs -- 1941-1950.; University of Michigan -- Students -- Social life and customs -- 1951-1960.; University of Michigan -- Students -- Social life and customs -- 1961-1970.; University of Michigan -- Students -- Social life and customs -- 1971-1980.; University of Michigan -- Students -- Social life and customs -- 1981-1990.; University of Michigan -- Students.; University of Michigan -- Student housing.; University of Michigan -- Students -- Societies, etc.; University of Michigan. Vice-President for Student Affairs.; University of Michigan. Vice-President for Student Services.; William Monroe Trotter House (University of Michigan); Bursley, Joseph Aldrich, 1877-1950.; Cutler, Richard Loyd, 1925-; Johnson, Henry.; Knauss, Robert L.; Newell, Barbara W.; Lewis, James A.; Walter, Erich Albert.
- Joseph A. Bursley, Dean of Students, 1913-1950; 1925-1946
  The Joseph A. Bursley series comprises fourteen linear inches and consists of four subseries: Correspondence, Harmon Foundation Correspondence, South American Relations Correspondence, and Topical files. The three correspondence subseries are arranged chronologically within each run. Much of the correspondence reflects Bursley's tendency to take personal interest in student affairs. Bursley virtually exudes an aura of paternalism in his letters as he disciplines wayward youths. The fact that Bursley handled scholarships, student aid, fraternities, and housing in addition to student discipline, attests to the eclecticism of his job. The topical file here is an amalgam of Bursley materials which had been scattered amid subsequent Vice Presidents' files. It is here that Bursley's decisions on fraternity and housing problems are revealed.
  - Correspondence and Meetings
    - 1922-1923 (Box 1)
    - 1924-1925 (Box 1)
    - 1926-1927 (Box 1)
    - 1928 (Box 1)
    - 1929-1930 (Box 1)
    - 1931 (Box 1)
    - 1932 (Box 1)
    - 1933 (Box 1)
    - 1934 (Box 1)
    - 1935 (Box 1)
    - January-June, 1936 (Box 1)
    - July-December, 1936 (Box 1)
    - 1937 (Box 1)
    - 1938-1941 (Box 1)
    - 1942 (Box 1)
    - 1943 (Box 1)
    - 1944 (Box 1)
    - 1945-1947 (Box 1)
  - Harmon Foundation: Correspondence
    - 1923-1925 (Box 1)
    - 1926-1929 (Box 1)
    - 1930-1931 (Box 1)
    - 1932-1938 (Box 1)
  - South American Relations: Correspondence, 1940-1944
    - August 1940-March, 1941 (Box 1)
    - May-September 1941 (Box 1)
    - October 1941-June, 1942 (Box 1)
    - July-December, 1942 (Box 1)
    - January-June, 1943 (Box 1)
    - July-December, 1943 (Box 1)
    - January-June, 1944 (Box 1)
    - July-December, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Topical Files, 1913-1950
    - Administrative Taxonomy, 1931 (Box 1)
    - Committee on Undergraduate Studies, 1927 (Box 1)
    - Fraternities, 1913-1949
      - Academic Affairs, 1923-1943 (Box 1)
      - Deferred Rushing, 1913-1932 (Box 1)
      - Finances, 1938-1942 (Box 1)
      - Hell Week, 1927-1946 (Box 1)
      - Prohibition/Drinking, 1926-1935 (Box 1)
      - Resident Advisers, 1933-1949 (Box 1)
    - Housing, 1927-1946
      - Correspondence, 1937-1946 (Box 1)
      - Reports, 1927-1945 (Box 1)
      - Report on Rooming Houses (Fred Wahr), 1936 (Box 1)
    - Interfraternity Council, 1914-1947
      - Correspondence, 1914-1947 (Box 2)
      - National Conference, 1920-1944 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1926-1950 (Box 2)
    - Student Christian Association (Fresh Air Camp), 1935-1936 (Box 2)
    - Student Employment Bureau reports, 1921-1946 (Box 2)
- Erich A. Walter, Dean of Students and Director, Office of Student Affairs, 1925-1959; 1946-1954
  The Erich A. Walter records are thin but illuminating. Evidently this material originally consisted of fragments of three distinct topical files. These have been collapsed into one alphabetical file of eight linear inches. Even though the Walter material is fragmentary, the expansion of the office's responsibilities are discernible. Walter's handling of fraternity affairs, housing, counseling, and health services are fairly documented. The most interesting materials are the 1948 orientation scrapbook and the files on veterans. As the G.I. Bill opened the doors of higher education to a larger population, the Office for Student Affairs stepped up its efforts to reach out and inform these new students of the nuances of the University.
  - Topical Files (fragments of various files), 1925-1959
    - Committee on Student Affairs, 1931; 1952-1955; 2 volumes (Box 2)
    - Counseling Services, 1946-1952 (Box 2)
    - Faculty Evaluation, 1945-1947 (Box 2)
    - Fraternities, 1946-1954
      - Expansion, 1953-1954 (Box 2)
      - Fliers (Masters), 1953-1954 (Box 2)
      - Professional, 1946-1947 (Box 2)
    - Health Services, 1953-1957 (Box 2)
    - Housing Committee, 1942-1956; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Howe, Stewart (Alumni Service), 1952-1954 (Box 2)
    - Interfraternity Council (IFC), 1925-1959
      - Executive Committee/Council, 1925-1954 (Box 2)
      - Fraternity Presidents' Assembly, 1945-1954; 3 folders (Box 2)
      - National Conference, 1949-1953 (Box 2)
      - National Reports on Scholarship, 1929-1951 (Box 2)
      - National Scholarships, 1931-1952 (Box 2)
      - Pledge Training, 1954 (Box 2)
      - Rushing Code, 1943-1953 (Box 2)
      - Scholarship, 1935-1953 (Box 2)
      - Social, 1953-1959 (Box 2)
    - Scrapbook, 1948; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Veterans Academic Affairs, 1947 (Box 2)
    - Veterans Administration, 1946-1949 (Box 2)
    - Veterans Service Bureau, 1947-1950 (Box 2)
    - Veterans Subsistence, 1947-1948 (Box 2)
    - Willow [Run] Village, 1946-1951
      - Chapel, 1947-1950 (Box 2)
      - General, 1946-1948 (Box 2)
      - Nursery, 1948-1951 (Box 2)
      - Veterans Housing, 1946-1949 (Box 2)
      - West Lodge, 1946-1950 (Box 2)
    - Zerman, William Annual Reports (Drafts), 1952-1953 (Box 2)
- James A. Lewis, Vice-President for Student Affairs, 1908-1964; 1954-1964
  James A. Lewis oversaw an office reorganization which resulted in the creation of two historical files. One organized all correspondence with fraternities alphabetically by fraternity. This fraternities correspondence subseries comprises eighteen inches of the James A. Lewis series and includes material dating back to the Walter and Bursley eras. This is the first area a researcher should investigate to find how the administration dealt with social, academic, and individual problems with fraternities. Much of the material here reflects the work of assistants to the vice-president, William Zerman and William Cross. The second historical file is the Student Organization subseries which Lewis created in the May 1963 office reorganization. This subseries is arranged alphabetically by organization and contains material documenting organized student interests from 1908 to 1963. The materials in this subseries consists of correspondence, constitutions, memos, and fliers on a broad range of student groups. Files of interest are: American Student Union, Committee for Civil Rights, Gargoyle, J-Hop, Michigan Youth for Democratic Action, and Young Progressives of Michigan. The last Lewis subseries is a topical file documenting his administrative concerns for fraternities, student affairs, and student government.
  - Fraternities Correspondence (Includes materials from J.A. Bursley and E.A. Walter), 1920-1962
    - Acacia, 1928-1951 (Box 3)
    - Alpha Chi Sigma, 1925-1958 (Box 3)
    - Alpha Delta Phi, 1920-1958 (Box 3)
    - Alpha Epsilon Pi, 1946-1957 (Box 3)
    - Alpha Kappa Kappa, 1925-1946 (Box 3)
    - Alpha Kappa Lambda, 1922-1958 (Box 3)
    - Alpha Kappa Psi, 1928-1955 (Box 3)
    - Alpha Omega, 1932-1958 (Box 3)
    - Alpha Phi Alpha, 1922-1949 (Box 3)
    - Alpha Rho Chi, 1921-1958 (Box 3)
    - Alpha Sigma Phi, 1927-1956 (Box 3)
    - Alpha Tau Omega, 1921-1958 (Box 3)
    - Beta Theta Pi, 1927-1958 (Box 3)
    - Chi Phi, 1921-1956 (Box 3)
    - Chi Psi, 1923-1958 (Box 3)
    - Delta Chi, 1926-1958 (Box 3)
    - Delta Kappa Epsilon, 1923-1958 (Box 3)
    - Delta Sigma Phi, 1926-1959 (Box 3)
    - Delta Sigma Pi, 1921-1956 (Box 3)
    - Delta Tau Delta, 1923-1958 (Box 3)
    - Delta Theta Phi, 1925-1962 (Box 3)
    - Delta Upsilon, 1926-1958 (Box 3)
    - Kappa Alpha Psi, 1923-1958 (Box 3)
    - Kappa Sigma, 1923-1957 (Box 3)
    - Lambda Chi Alpha, 1921-1957 (Box 3)
    - Nu Sigma Nu, 1925-1958 (Box 3)
    - Phi Alpha Delta, 1925-1953 (Box 3)
    - Phi Chi, 1925-1956 (Box 3)
    - Phi Delta Chi, 1925-1954 (Box 3)
    - Phi Delta Epsilon, 1921-1955 (Box 3)
    - Phi Delta Phi, 1925-1957 (Box 3)
    - Phi Delta Theta, 1922-1959 (Box 3)
    - Phi Epsilon Pi, 1921-1958 (Box 3)
    - Phi Gamma Delta, 1923-1958 (Box 3)
    - Phi Kappa Psi, 1925-1958 (Box 3)
    - Phi Kappa Sigma, 1925-1958 (Box 3)
    - Phi Kappa Tau, 1923-1956 (Box 3)
    - Phi Mu Alpha, 1924-1940 (Box 3)
    - Phi Rho Sigma, 1926-1949 (Box 3)
    - Phi Sigma Delta, 1923-1958 (Box 3)
    - Phi Sigma Kappa, 1922-1953 (Box 3)
    - Pi Lambda Phi, 1922-1958 (Box 3)
    - Psi Omega, 1925-1960 (Box 3)
    - Psi Upsilon, 1925-1954 (Box 3)
    - Sigma Alpha Epsilon, 1922-1958 (Box 3)
    - Sigma Alpha Mu, 1921-1958 (Box 3)
    - Sigma Chi, 1923-1957 (Box 3)
    - Sigma Nu, 1921-1958 (Box 3)
    - Sigma Phi, 1923-1958 (Box 3)
    - Sigma Phi Epsilon, 1926-1957 (Box 3)
    - Tau Delta Phi, 1922-1958 (Box 4)
    - Tau Epsilon Phi, 1922-1958 (Box 4)
    - Tau Epsilon Rho, 1922-1946 (Box 4)
    - Tau Kappa Epsilon, 1924-1958 (Box 4)
    - Theta Chi, 1925-1956 (Box 4)
    - Theta Delta Chi, 1928-1958 (Box 4)
    - Theta Xi, 1925-1958 (Box 4)
    - Triangle, 1925-1958 (Box 4)
    - Trigon, 1925-1957 (Box 4)
    - Zeta Beta Tau, 1924-1957 (Box 4)
    - Zeta Psi, 1925-1957 (Box 4)
  - Student Organizations (Historical File), 1908-1965
    - Adelphi Literacy Society, 1909 (Box 4)
    - All Campus Peace Committee, 1938-1941 (Box 4)
    - Alpha Phi Omega, 1939-1959 (Box 4)
    - American Student Union, 1935-1942 (Box 4)
    - American Veterans Committee, 1946-1961 (Box 4)
    - Ann Arbor Direct Action Committee, 1960-1961 (Box 4)
    - Anti-War Society (Michigan), 1938-1939 (Box 4)
    - Aristolochite Society, 1908 (Box 4)
    - Art Cinema League, 1948-1950 (Box 4)
    - Arts Chorale, 1949-1954 (Box 4)
    - Assembly, 1946-1954 (Box 4)
    - Baha'i Student Group, 1943-1944 (Box 4)
    - Baptist (Southern) Student Union, 1959 (Box 4)
    - Business Administration Council, 1946-1959 (Box 4)
    - Central Pep Rally Committee, 1951-1959 (Box 4)
    - Chamber of Commerce Club, 1922-1939 (Box 4)
    - Cheerleaders, 1931-1957 (Box 4)
    - Chinese Student Club, 1944-1956 (Box 4)
    - Christian Medical Society, 1953-1965 (Box 4)
    - Civil Liberties Committee, 1951-1954 (Box 4)
    - Committee for Civil Rights, 1948-1956 (Box 4)